welcome to voices with verveiki i'm
joined once again
with my friend and colleague jp marceau
uh jp and i have had a series of very
uh engaging and enriching uh
conversations
uh jp why don't you just reintroduce
yourself a bit and then let's launch us
into
uh the deal logos for today yeah thank
you john for having me again
um yeah i have a background in
philosophy because i was interested
in solving let's say my own sliver of
the the meaning crisis how it appeared
to me and
my philosophical studies allowed me to
try and address this
i especially became uh familiar with
pancychism as a way to address one of
the aspects of the knee crisis sort of
the
the idea that maybe i'm just matter or
that my consciousness is
somehow disconnected from my body and
you know
over the course of becoming aware of uh
jordan peterson's work
jonathan's work your work eventually was
able to
get in touch with you and have a
dialogue more precisely about psychism
and something interesting happened in
there where it turned out that
let's see the reasons why i was trying
to use that psychism to address my
sliver of limiting crisis you were also
able to address
with your non-reductive uh physicalism
and some of the the the points some of
the problems are really mirrored there
so in psychism
the the problem of the one in the many
shows up really clearly in passangism
because
you know how is it that different
consciousnesses can somehow combine
because that's all
climate and psychism if consciousness
goes all the way all the way down and
that's the reason why we have
consciousnesses
then you need to explain how it is at
those smaller consciousnesses my
my cells are atoms so how is it that
they can combine
yeah yeah and i was to use some
bergsonian uh
uh ideas to get uh get clear with that
and
bergson was very influenced from
neoplatonism so on the other end when i
was talking about
with you and it turned out that your
with your non-reductive physicalism
you make use of neoplatonic ideas to
explain what's
the same basic idea of the problem of
the one in domain doesn't show up in
terms of consciousness itself but still
you have the problem of how is it that
some abstract patterns some
unify the entities some some formal
structures can interact with their
constituents in a way that
allows them to be at the same time one
and many
so we have sort of parallel sets of of
concerns and
throughout uh the last year really
because it's been
just a bit over a year i think since we
last spoke i
i've been more and more exploring this
idea of emergency elimination and to see
how much i can get
from a more standard naturalistic
ontology
without without having to go full-blown
psychism uh
already and this this led us especially
uh to converge on the thought of a new
platonic christian thinkers such as john
scottish regina and also saint maximus
the confessor
yep and really over the the course of
the just the last
few months i've been rereading some uh
authors that
i had read more in depth a few years ago
such as saint thomas
aquinas and was able to find
this basic pattern of emergence and
elimination
in aquinas as well and
what i was interested to figure out
today in our discussion was
some of the the reasons why this
this this dialectical worldview between
emergency animation was
was not clearer to me or to people in
general whereas i think you can find it
in aquinas or
even to go further back um jonathan
pedro's brother
matthew wrote the book the language of
creation uh commentary on the symbolic
uh
on basically on genesis and he makes
quite clear in
this book although it wasn't clear at
the time when i read it two years ago
but
when i reread it now knowing what i know
now about emergency
nation although matthew uses different
language
it's clear to me that you can see the
same
pattern between images and lamination uh
right
right away from the start of genesis in
the beginning god created the events
the forms from which uh structures are
made and created the earth which is
which was without form and void so
that's just the potential from which
things will emerge
yeah so this was surprising for me to to
see this uh recently and
i was interested to see so not only how
is it that
this dialectical view of emergency
nation
was became let's say unclear to us today
and i was thinking that it probably has
to do with the dialectic
across people or across thinkers as well
where
we have become it's not only that our
world view has become let's see flatter
where we have a harder time thinking of
how different layers and track together
but one of the reasons why
older traditions were able to have
richer ontologies
such as you find in aquinas or also in
in the
the uh in israel was that they also had
the
much more dialectical view of society in
general or of people's
roles so the best philosophers
tended to be priests people were
actually in contact with a lot of people
they were able to sort of abstract from
the lives of all the parishioners
and they also had to mediate between
them and higher levels uh
in in the hierarchy so they were living
the metaphysics that they were trying to
lay out in books
yeah and i think that our loss of this
metaphysics
is really paralleled by our loss of our
myth
our uh tactical relationships in general
yeah
yeah i think that's wow that's really
beautiful uh
jp so there's a lot in there i'd like to
respond to
uh if you give me a bit of time because
yeah yeah sure
that was really rich so i don't know if
you know enough but i'm working on an
anthology called internet or dialogues
uh with christopher master pietro we're
editing it contributing to
and what we've got is people from uh
paul's uh paul vanderbilt is
contributing to it
uh we have people uh from many spots of
what
sevilla king calls this corner of the
internet she's interested too
all these people involved with these
emerging practices and all this dialogue
um and and what
and what chris and i are exploring is
um the effort by many of these like the
circling communities
uh the evolved community right uh
all of these new biological communities
um and even uh other communities like
great
great kelly that incorporate a
dialogical component to it
all these all these practices all these
biological practices are an emergence
so what we're trying to do is um
figure out what is going on there
that's one thing and then i'm
what really what sparked my interest in
this was
a couple things i had a discussion with
jordan hall and he talked about the need
for
a meta psycho technology uh that
curates and coordinates the ecology of
practices then i realized
for the ancient world that was dialectic
so i've engaged in the long project of
trying to sort of
reverse engineer what dialectic is as a
practice
um and so there's lots of stuff you know
lots of videos about that
the book is coming out anyways where
that is leading me
is uh into
a lot of the the the ideas that you just
said
one is the idea that dialectic always
had a horizontal
and a vertical aspect to it there was a
horizontal aspect
in which you and i you and i are both
engaged in projects of individuation and
particip
and participation right uh because and
every human being is
until i talked about that and young has
a similar kind of notion
that we're locked into this this tone us
this creative tension
uh between individuation and
participation and then what we're doing
in that right is that there is often
between
us and emergent logos and like you and i
and this is this is one of the for me
one of this is one of the features of
media logos uh i prefer to use the greek
rather than the modern term
um uh in in contrast to normal debate
or even conversation is that you and i
together can get to a place we couldn't
get to on our own yeah
right yeah it's exactly the the
terminology that you can you can find in
it's not the exact same terminology but
the same idea that you can find in other
areas that are popping up right now so
let's say the in the the emergence
notion in modern philosophy of minor
cognitive science you did
when a new system has properties
that you cannot reduce to the individual
constituents then you have a new
emergent
uh system that is not reducible or if
you you take the
the older uh notion of form from
aristotle or aquinas
well a a form it is substantial form
in opposition to a mere accidental
aggregate of things a
substantial form is a pattern that you
cannot produce
to its four constituents it has
attributes that are
it has new causal powers that you don't
find at lower levels
exactly so that's exactly right so
you've got this notion of emergence of
new logos
right new properties new patterns it's
and it's because it's an inhib it has a
formal cause
which i interpret dynamically to mean a
system is self-organizing
as you said not a mere aggregation or a
heap it's self-organizing and especially
it's self-organizing in
some way that's self-perpetuating and
self-preserving and that's
right and so the idea is there's that
horizontal dimension
but that is always in connection with it
exemplifies
and is informed by the vertical
dimension because
as you and i in dial in dialectic we're
not
just getting an intimacy with each other
and i mean that
right as a kind of intimacy of
intellection and intelligibility
as we do that we also get an intimacy
with that very process of
intelligibility
emerging and what that takes us into is
the fact
is that intelligibility is also
something that as you said
that is level that is moving between
emergence right and in the dialogue you
and i will have as you said something
emerged
with the insight but there's also a
sense
when you're engaged in the horizontal
dialogue there's also a sense of
emanation
because you don't you you're not just
arbitrarily saying things
there right there's a sense of right
that we're uncovering the structures of
intelligibility the very structures by
which we can make sense of the world
and they're they're ahead of us in some
way yeah there's like meaningful
constraints
above us that no tell us where we could
take the conversation
and we can sort of just select between
them that's right
so you start to in the horizontal
between the individuation and the
participation
you also start to find yourself
exemplifying
the vertical move right between the
emergence
and the emanation you start to engage in
a process of anagarge
so as you and i reciprocally open
horizontally there's also a reciprocal
opening
vertically and and so dialectic becomes
a profound act by which we
simultaneously realize our humanity
because we're
making each other more persons
right because we're realizing
actualizing our our personhood
but but but we're also realizing you
know
what what what what undergirds all
realness those patterns of
intelligibility those layers
of relationship between emergence
and emanation so you and so
i don't think it's a coincidence i
mentioned you this earlier before we
just started filming
i don't think it's coincidence that you
find you know erigina writing in a
dialogue fashion
and thomas aquinas in the summer writing
in a dialogical fashion i don't think
that's a coincidence
i don't think it's just a mere sort of
pleasantry or ornamentation
i think they're trying to exemplify in
the form
because they're aware of formal cause
you're trying to exemplify
in the form of the dialogue right the
dialectic
they're not just talking about things
they're exemplifying and they're
and what they're trying to do is make
the pattern of the
co-presentation of ideas are fine to
be offended like have an affinity to you
know the very pattern by which
reality is presence in between emanation
and emergence and i think that's a
profound realization when you do some of
these practices
right like the practice the dialectic
into the
logos or sense uh guys send stocks uh
circling practice
everybody gets this sense of this uh
third factor
that there's a between it
and i don't mean this disrespectful you
know i don't mean that you know jesus
notion
where two or three are gathered in my
name there i am also when you're doing
these practices
everybody gets a sense of the we space
i've talked to you this before
that somehow beyond so the between
also immediately makes people
phenomenologically aware
of the above and beyond and so those two
dimensions i've talked about them
abstractly but when it happens
it's not an abstract experience it's a
palpable
sense presence that is profoundly
enriching and transformative to people
so this whole project of dialectic
uh i think is actually very very central
and so i think the degree to which we've
lost the practice of dialectic
we have lost access to the horizontal
and vertical dimensions and then that as
you already argued i thought very
astutely
that truncates our metaphysics in a way
that really hamstrings us
and helps drive the meeting crisis
that's what i would argue that's what i
would propose to you yeah and
i i think one aspect of it is when we we
talk about it's the vertical
aspects of dialectic the fact that
aquinas for instance was writing
metaphysical books
uh where as you brightly point out the
the suma is written as a dialectic
between its
objections and responses but you know in
his
in his vocation aquinas was also a
priest where his job was to be
a mediator between a cosmic dialectic
you know
he he has to listen to people's
confessions yes
yeah yeah he listens you can sit as
he gathers the potential of his parish
and of his students
so people freedoms of uh refined
information and
he has to bring it all up into himself
and try to
make it fit within uh christianity
within it
yeah yeah yeah with it within something
super abstract something invisible
within evan you know the realm of the
invisibles virtual reality and
aquinas has to mediate between
all of those and i think that all of the
the mess that we see in in philosophy
starting
starting probably with modernity is in
large part due to the fact that people
stopped doing this dialectic uh
with other people also across people and
so for instance it's it this was really
striking to me when i
did uh when i was in grad school in in
philosophy and
taking different seminars let's see you
take a seminar in analytic philosophy in
a seminar in phenomenology
and you can clearly see that this isn't
just the thing about let's see some
people think that phenomology is better
and some people think that
analytics philosophy of mind is better
like people at different personalities
like
you can tell that they were largely
influenced by the way they interact with
the world
and so this the loss of a dialectic
between people in the academia and the
loss of directing between the people of
the academy and the real people like the
people in the pew
this this loss of dialectic that
connected people and that allowed them
to reach a ir dialectic
is what has led to the huge
fragmentation that we see today in
philosophy departments or between
departments in the university as well
where if you talk to someone in
literature or someone in physics they'll
have wildly different cultures whereas
that wasn't the time if you went back to
a time when
people had more meta unified metaphysics
or when the uni
the university was more unified and this
really concerns me because i
i'm not sure how we can recover this
sort of
better centered metaphysics nowadays i
think that's right i mean
i mean yeah there's several problems
there one one is
the problem that i'm trying to address
with a bunch of people which is
can we bring back simultaneously
the practice of dialectic
and situated home it within
a world view that legitimates it and
valorizes it
um but then there's and i'll talk about
that in more in a sec but then
i don't want to forget the other point
you made but there's also you know
there's also a social institutional
issue
about how we've separated the monastery
uh right from the university
and that has led to what you i think
you're discussing here
so let's not lose that point but let's
come back to the first point
um so i think
that point you made about human beings
living
uh especially people who had a a
mediating function
um it's also very very um
apropos because if you look to the
father of dialectic
socrates um he sees himself
as always mataksu always in always
mediating
uh between right um always between
uh the divine and the human and even
sees eros
as something that is uh between the
divine and the human
uh and so that the sense of uh
of being something that inherently
mediates
between what emerges and what's emanate
is is very very pregnant
uh in socrates uh and then it gets
carried through and
developed you know very extensively
as you know in the neoplatonic tradition
yeah
yeah and so even you know within my
tradition within the jewel christian
tradition
yep you you have you have prophets or
you know you have priests you have
people who mediate between
uh the people and god they're never just
like trying to bring the people to
themselves they're always trying to turn
the people ultimately to god to the our
story even christ
when he comes down he says that he's
always just trying to get people to the
father like it's not about
himself it's not about just him
gathering people or him having something
below him fit well it's always about
mediating between creation and the
creator
right right but also exemplifying so
he's
right he's gathering people the logos
into like there's
the emergence of the of the church right
very much but but he's also uh he's also
exemplifying right yeah he's emanating
right uh he's emanating i i
i don't again i'm worried that i'm well
you and i know each other you know that
i don't know
he's he's in some sense he's emanating
god and that sounds like a heresy but
you know the language i'm trying well
yeah he's
we can just say that he's emanating the
father yes that's fine
yeah so what what what
what what i think happens though is
that like
there's a historical issue i think you
get the shift
right uh from the dialogue
to the to the treatise and you get the
shift
to non-transformational purely
propositional thinking
and you get figures like akam and so
forth um
and you get nominalism which
some at the same time removes the sense
of there being these layers and these
patterns
and then you get the rise of that sort
of monolithic
isolated individual mind removed like so
in the ecclesia you really have a a
version
i don't want to be too anatomistic here
you have something like an understanding
of distributed cognition
that most of our cognition is done in an
embodied fashion in which we are
embedded
with people in distributed cognition
that we that most of our
most of our reasoning is and should be
done in concert with other people and
that's what the cognitive science is now
showing that our cognition is
distributed has extended
uh the work of my friend greg henricus
and the work of
mercier and sperver that reasoning
argumentation
works better in in in concert with other
people
than on your own so that monolithic
monological
mind model i think um
has been very very disastrous uh it
actually has cut us off
and the cog side i would argue is now
returning us
um to the view of the importance of the
horizontal and it's also simultaneously
and you
you you've already alluded to this
starting to return us to
right the vertical because it's
reminding us uh that we
are well at least the the kind of
cognitive science that
i i practice this discussion uh
bottom-up processes of emergence and
top-down processes of constraint
are now rife through for e-cognitive
science and profound way
and so the vertical and the horizontal
dimensions are coming back
into uh prominence and precisely the
time i think when they're most
culturally needed
what that means back now to the second
point sorry i'm talking so much today
but the second point about what the
institution will look like i don't know
what i see happening is i've seen these
new emerging
ecologies and practices that i've gone
to like conferences like
the movement summit and i've been on
panel and talking about
and again no disrespect but they seem to
be trying to bridge
between the separate functions of the
university
and the monastery these communities are
are schooling people like the academy
but they're also demanding but and
affording
self-transformation and
self-transcendence and community
building
like the monastery like when you look at
what rafe is doing it's
it's it's like it's i said this to me
he's telling me about all of these
things and i said
you know ray if you're actually building
a church and he laughed he sort of
acknowledged that there was something
going on there
and so i think that
perhaps i'm trying to be very cautious
here this emerging
cognitive science understanding of the
horizontal and vertical dimensions
that are realized india logos
is coming more and more into contact
with maybe i'm a mediator
i just thought about that that's a joke
coming in contact with
these emerging communities that are
trying to create
institutions or communities that are
between
or beyond the division of the school and
the monastery
but they sometimes call themselves even
secular monasteries or this school or
that school
so i think that's what i see happening
sorry that was a lot but i wanted to
answer
you you keep saying very pregnant things
yeah that's good i i'd like to
try and bring something related i have
never
sort of tried to think about the history
of
last time in our last discussion we
talked about the idea of christianity
spreading through deaths and reverts
and i have never tried to think about it
explicitly in terms of
dialectic i've tried to think about it
in related terms and i think maybe it
could help us
in this discussion right now but
what seems to have happened is uh okay
so
we talked about metaphysics going awry
in the west
we talk also about how the surrounding
institutions
uh went awry uh also and i think
i i i i've been playing with the idea
that you can
see this as a within a an even broader
historical dialectic maybe of
okay so in as i i alluded to
you can see already in the hebrew
scriptures this dialectical worldview
going on between heaven and earth
between the forms
the invisible and the the matter the
potential
jacob's ladder yeah you can you can
already see this in in the old testament
fairly clearly i think especially in
matthew
matthews book i think it like gives so
many examples that it's quite
overwhelming
um and then when
judaism will become christianity later
it will spread both east and west
and what seems to have happened as it
spread especially in the east or let's
say in atlantic culture
it includes rome at the time you had a
culture where
people were largely platonists
especially uh in the intelligentsia
where
people were or in general the illinois
philosophers were
used to see the world in terms of
emanation the they didn't think
so much about the the matter they didn't
think that god created matter
uh the potential they thought that god
lets it be a mover or the form of forms
or
the one that from this this form from
this
this set of constraints from this source
of constraints we can even say
uh shapes will come to uh
give order to the the potential of
matter so you have this top-down view of
the world
whereas with uh so so when christianity
spreads
in the east in illinois culture
the challenge will be to get people to
see that but marketing as well because
there's yeah that god created
matter as well and that there are
genuine there's genuine emergence so the
challenge was to sort of get the
the greeks and the romans to care about
the body uh at least the philosopher
so the kind of resistance that you'll
see is a way
errors is where people sort of have this
name for matter or uh
you have origin who has word theories
about matter or about
sometimes maybe the body being that's
this it's sorry maybe you can sit as a
as a soldier of down source of
everything yeah yeah
and what happened in the west uh is sort
of the opposite you had like germanic
tribes were fairly materialistic
and i um there's i think it's um
his name is gibson right now i read a
book from a an author
brett saw called which uh paul directly
out on his channel yet good
conversations and
he wrote a book on the history of trans
substantiation uh yes
yes and he references a in the book he
references an author
whose name escapes me uh it's a catholic
theologian
who makes the point that the germanic
cultures
were fairly materialistic not only
you can sit sometimes in roman documents
like the romans will uh
sort of mock the the germanic tries
because they they venerate
visible things like they're not able to
abstract as much to the invisible
and also there's also the fact that
because they were always warring with
one another tended to make them more
pragmatic
and to sort of make them really
down-to-earth people right so
what happens as a christianity spreads
uh in europe and the european tribes
become
uh converted and have now
they were fine with seeing the world
bottom up seeing like concrete things
uh but they have to start to see that
god created the evans as well like that
god is behind both heaven and earth that
is beyond
emergence and elimination and now the
the source of eresis that you'll see is
that they stand to see the world just
so already in like the 8th or 9th
century when
you not only have romans doing theology
there but when
especially like the germanic tribes
start doing their own philosophy
anthology you can start to see rscs
where
people will only see the bottom up
aspect of things and they sort of make
more and more receiving the uh the
emanation from evan
right and so in the case of uh of the
eucharist you start to see disputes
about people saying that well
either it means that the eucharist is
like in
even in the accidents is flesh and flesh
and blood just like my flesh and blood
like the same flesh and blood that was
on the cross
or you'll start to see people doing well
then it means that it's just a symbol
and symbol in sort of the the pederative
sense that it's
it's just a symbol so i think what has
happened is
okay so you had like within the judo
christian culture especially from
like the early hebrew heritage you have
a worldview where both emergent
animation work really well
in the in the in the east when julia
christianity its
calendar culture now the challenge is to
see the apartment thing as well
but when it moves west the challenge is
to see that top down as well
and i think that what has happened
especially
no throughout the years throughout
modernity the west
by seeing the world uh bottom up
and you know making a bunch of
theological errors but because
the uh which is it maybe that the church
or the judeo-christian worldview
because it still improved upon what was
already there
uh it sort of gave power to the the
the bottom-up worldview of the germanic
tribes and led to science and it's only
just compounded because you were
seeing real successes by seeing the
world only bottom up but it's only
recently started to
to fragment this worldview we realize
that if you only try to see things
bottom up you hit like tons of problems
that you've seen in foster field even
just chemistry
it's not clear how you can explain the
emergence really
of chemical compounds that have
properties that you don't seem to be
able to reduce to their individual
components or
same thing that happens with life it's
huge problem with consciousness if you
don't have
like genuine emergence if you don't have
genuine forms that
will then emanate down to to the matter
it you can't really explain
consciousness either
so overall i said that in my more
optimistic days i see that
is i don't try to just some people when
they see that okay christianity went
wrong there or went from there they
tried to
sort of respond respond as a reactionary
just
then then let's just roll back to the
last thing that worked and the sort of
let's stay there
you can see this in protestants or even
some uh
some like traditional catholics or
orthodox they just oh if we just go back
to the church fathers or if you just go
back to aquarius and everything will be
fine
but i more tend to think that like it's
all part of one story where
this see this world view where emerges
and mentioned were
meeting well in the judo christian
tradition like as it spreads east
it has a certain dielectric to go
through until it reaches a more stable
point and same thing
in in the west where you still have to
go through like cycles of
of dialectic to get people to see the
top down in the bottom up as well
do you think that helps yeah wait i like
this i think this is a really brilliant
idea a new way of uh a new schema for
interpreting
uh the history of christianity i think
that's really cool
so let me make sure i get you that
and you started top down but at the end
you also alluded bottom up which is
well done by the way uh so
but let me so i might be presenting in
reverse order the way you present it but
this is your way uh making you
understand
like both east and west have a dialectic
between bottom down and top
uh between bottom up and top down right
between emergence and emanation
but the but nevertheless overall the
east tends to emphasize
emanation and the west can stand precise
emergence
and so there's also a higher order
dialect between the east and west
it is very fruitful right now it's worth
saying that right now the dialogues are
really cool like
happening between the catholics and the
orthodox or doing the protestants and
the catholics and the orthodox like
this this plant is i don't know if it
will really get get fixed
in our lifetimes but at least there is a
very fruitful directive that wasn't
going on 100 years ago
yes but first of all did i understand
you correctly did i
got you okay so that is a very cool idea
uh that's almost a hegelian idea i mean
i have forms with
hegel's understanding of the dialectic
um uh
but nevertheless that it's almost like
um the dialectic within the church
right within history uh there's also a
dialectic within history you're saying
uh that is exemplified in the history of
the church um because it's exemplifying
now that strikes me as
plausible at least prima facie precisely
because i think
that uh processes of distributed
cognition
which is what churches are um are going
to be inherently
dialectical in nature and precisely
because i think
um ultimately that has to do with
something with the structure of reality
itself
as well so i think that again both the
vertical between people
and sorry the horizontal between people
and the vertical between the the sort of
levels of your ontology
both cry out for a dialectical approach
so what you're suggesting is that
even if people weren't consciously or
deliberately
practicing dialectic nevertheless
there's dialectical processing is still
at work
uh within their history is that a fair
thing to say
yes yes i think we're embedded in all
kinds of levels of dialectic that we're
not obviously not
aware of completely well that means
another function of dialectic
is by is through exemplification
to actually explicate and make bring
into self-consciousness
the fact that we instantiate and
exemplify
layers of dialectic that's so there's an
aspect of
self-consciousness and coming to
self-realization
that would be an additional function of
the practice of dialectic so whereas
what you've said is often people this is
happening implicitly
and unawares but when people can
like like are gena or aquinas when they
can explicitly take up
dialectic they can exemplify and bring
into awareness bring into
self-consciousness
those implicit patterns do i do i think
well yeah yeah yeah i think you you can
see it as
within this all it's a cosmic historical
dialectic that's appearing there will be
like pockets where
this uh dialectic is exemplified best
and around which like
more pockets of proper relationship
between emergency animation
will spread yeah so yeah so you can see
sort of uh original and aquinas
as playing a part in the larger story
and they
like they can't fix it all all the way
by themselves like the whole process of
the west having to go to the end
of its bottom-up uh view of the world to
realize that it doesn't work like
aquinas and the original were able to
like contribute to pockets of of harmony
in that all uh
yeah yeah that whole schema but it's
still stake
it still takes hundreds of years to
unfold i mean it's it's it's a long
process
but but thank you for saying that but
i i just there's a there's something
here
that came out for me as a as an insight
this idea that
i almost want to say like there's
another dimension to dialectic
there's the horizontal between people
there's the vertical there's the
ontological
but there's the historical we are
embedded always
in processes dialectical processes
and one of the things we can do is bring
them and this does sound more like
kegel's notion of dialectic
we can bring them into um self-awareness
we can realize them
and then and that's an additional
function of dialectic
thank you for this i know that you're i
know that you're
you're fairly critical of narratives
though so yeah
like especially you know i i think this
dialectical worldview of history i can
make sense of it within
christianity but i would be curious you
know what would be your reserves
ah so so um
that's a very good point there's um
i can't remember his name his last name
strong he's on my discord server
and he's been writing to me and he said
don't you think that dialectic is
is a kind of narrative but he called it
a non-teleological
narrative because he he says it doesn't
have it doesn't have
right the the typical structure i mean
the typical structure
you have you know you have the
protagonist right and
they have to overcome right the
antagonist and
and there is the climax and the denim
and right
and the problem is resolved so it's a
finite game as cars would say
and that's the structure and i've come
increasingly
realized that i because
i've over identified that as narrative
to core
i think to be a little bit fair to
myself precisely because i think the
culture
has over identified that with narrative
to core but
i think what uh what's coming out in the
discussion with strawn
is the idea that dialectic is kind of
trans
narrative um it's it's so james carson
going to be talking to him
you know our traditional notions of
narrative
right like the the story right
are finite they they're the point is for
them to come to an end
right but the point of the logos because
it's the point
because it's about enacting emergence
and emanation
it's an infinite game the point is it's
not supposed to conclude
it's supposed to continually afford the
re-realization of right relationship
to yourself to each other and to the
world right
and so he was saying but isn't it in
that sense
like if you could if you could say sort
of the finite structure of narrative at
least this was what i took him to say
and he seemed to agree when i gave it
back to him i hope i'm not imposing on
him
but if you take the finite structure of
narrative and you were
to unfold it into what cars called an
infinite game
right where the point is not to uh come
to a conclusion
right and it's not primarily
oppositional where
the protagonist is supposed to overcome
the antagonist
but it's like what happens in dear logos
isn't that kind of trans narrative
in an important way and i thought that
was really interesting because
my one of my critiques of narrative
is it seems to at times
i gotta be really careful here it seems
to
limit people to
a sort of a linguistic imagistic
level of cognition and for me
that it doesn't make enough space for
home for the mystical dimension for
where people experience
non-propositional like states of
transformation
but i think given what we were saying a
bit earlier
you can see dialogos if properly
understood as trans narrative
mediates between finite narrative
and the mystical that's something that
i'm sort of playing around with as an
idea right now
yeah yeah i think that that makes sense
and i just you you probably saw my eyes
lighter because
it mapped on to something like a tension
within i should say attention between
like two two poles of one phenomena
within
uh the christian worldview it's there's
okay the idea that
you can see the narrative that's laid
out in christianity as
a as a if sort of finite story with a
start
a middle and an end and that's it you
can see okay so
god creates the character the world at
that time and then he came
at this time and then uh you'll come
back at that time
so it's it's one one way to see it but
you can also see that the events
all of these events all of these events
of creation like actually occur all the
time
like the way creation always unfolds at
every instant is always from the
structure
so god always uh emanates forms from
heaven he always emanates uh
potential uh all of these always meet to
create the event in the earth and
everything in between it always comes
back to god we always mess it up with a
fall
and then uh there's always like some
potential that will stop back up to save
us
and we'll be judged against that
potential and we come back to paradise
that's
when when christ let's say dies on the
cross uh
he says to the the one to the good thief
uh today you'll be with me in paralyzed
paris is a direct
you know coming back to to paris to the
garden in eden so
like it looks back not to let's say
finally import mystery necessarily but
it goes back also
to uh the the let's say the restart of
the story like restarting the dialectic
you can see
and so you can see the narrative as
both like occurring in time with a start
and an end
and you can also sit okay every instant
and what occurs at every instant is the
much more let's say mystical part
the the part that you know demand that
recovers
uh transformation that can actually
apply to your life right now it's a
point that
sometimes um people will like priests
will say in homilies but if we read
let's say
parts of the of revelation or the
apocalypse if we read parts of
press pronouncements about the end of
the world and if we think that it only
like
matters for let's say that day when the
end time comes that it means that like
almost all christians for almost all of
us three will have read this for nothing
like because
yeah yeah yeah but we should like see
this
occurring at their instant and so we
should like
always be in directing we do i mean i do
think that
there is such a thing as see a global
history
of this pattern that will actually it's
it's
i'm not sure what the end will be
because it's described as a city or as a
garden so it's not like it will be a
state where nothing changes but i do
think
that it will unfold across time i think
it is i'm falling across time but i also
think that at the same time
we can like immediate between this story
that takes forever and
our own lives right now and apply all of
this spiritually
i would agree with that uh uh to a large
degree
precisely because one way you can think
of mythos
is precisely as something that's trans
narrative in the way i'm talking
because you get a story in it a myth or
even
or even more so a parable right that
looks like a finite story
but it's not right it actually sets you
into
uh an infinite an infinite uh sort of
trans-narrative dialectic
um and so uh myths
i think in that when properly understood
uh and
and i think they're they're improperly
misunderstood when people
and this is the the sin of literal
literalism where you
you you bind it into a particular uh
time and place and location
um you make it a purely finite story
rather than seeing that
the prodigal son for example the parable
is something that is going to occur me
occur to me every day and and and there
is no conclusion to the
the parable of the prodigal son of you
like when people just allegorize it and
come to a conclusion
i think that's almost blasphemous in
some ways i'm sorry my language is
getting very religious here
um but um uh because i mean
at different points in my life i have
found that i identify and take the
perspective of different players
in that little drama and what i've come
to realize is that story doesn't
conclude
it's always a perpetual time bomb that
will go off and remind me
that in my pursuit of justice i have to
remember compassion
and in my exemplification of compassion
i cannot
destroy the structures of justice and
that there is
that there is a recognition of human
finitude but also human aspirations
right and all of that i have to keep
remembering because i will
i will tend towards extremes and i will
tend
to gravitate to those sinkholes of local
you know local minimal right but what
the parable does
right this little finite piece of text
puts me in the infinite dialectic where
i'm constantly moving between
individuation and participation
i'll use your language between heaven
and earth and i never stop
i never stop and that's what it is to
grab
i think to not grab that's the wrong
word to grasp to grasp
a parable and to be grabbed by it that's
what i wanted to say
that's what i would argue that myth
mythos and parable
right are the language they're sort of
the
they're kind of the artistic twin
to what you see in more propositional
language within
uh dialectic but this comes out in the
practice when you're doing these
practices with people
they move between their statements and
all
of the all these metaphorical poetic
gestures that they actually enact over
and over again
and they get a sense of these deeper
patterns
that are repeating throughout their
lives coming to the fore
yeah cool i'd like to try to bring it
back to
us today uh in 2020 because if
my best guess you know regarding this
whole historical
uh dialectic
right now we're i don't think we're
seeing the end of a let's say
a strictly bottom-up world view of just
trying to see matter and all
how it combines and you know this
mirrors a breakdown in our view of
let's say social systems where we have
all kinds of social systems that are
breaking down
dialectic isn't working really within
the university it's not really working
within individual in society between
groups and society and so on yeah let's
see sort of this this widespread
uh collapse in our our systems
but on the other end you see the
emergence of new systems like you
mentioned all of the
the the movement submits and so on like
new emerging
practices that promise to on the one end
they emerge
through dialectic through people like
interacting with one another and across
communities
and from this emerges finer and finer uh
sets of practices and institutions and
so on that will take the place of the
fading ones
and you know on the other end i do think
that even within
within cuchinity you see this as well we
we touched on it just a bit last time
and i did
i was a bit more mindful of it recently
but you do
there's definitely a shift going on
within well i just
especially within christianity because
that's the one i know most i know that
people are moving away from
more sort of simplistic uh
non-liturgical uh kinds of practices
people are moving back and see
even within the protestant churches
they're moving to more liturgical
practices
people moving uh sometimes right away to
either catholic or
uh orthodox uh denominations because you
know
they have richer world views more
dialectic across people
and more than just even like in the
setting of a church where you do
dialectic you know with your neighbors
and also with your priests with you
this is richer that i think is richer in
the older traditions within the catholic
church there's like
it's it may actually be a problem of
like so many people want to move back
that it's uh some yeah it may cause
problems like people want their masses
back in latin and so on
uh and like the older churches are
gathering more people
so you see like emerging with even
within the church certain
sets of practices certain theologies
being more
uh favored than others so like by
trying to to tend to those favorable
emerging
positions right i do have just because
of my christian commitments
and seeing this world view as viable to
me i do have like
a fair amount of hope in all of this
that this will be heading in a good
direction
doesn't mean that it will be good
necessarily for us churches have gone
extinct and so on but
like that overall the course of this
dialectic will be in a positive
direction and i'm
fairly comfortable with just tending the
garden where i
attending the the places where the the
emergence where i see the emergence of
good aspects of the standard i don't
know exactly what it will look like in
practice but
i let's say we there's something really
good occurring in this corner of the
internet i think so i do my best to try
to foster
this one i agree with that i think
people are
hungry for mythos and given our
discussion
this is this is enmeshed with
a hunger uh for for dear logos
and for practices like dialectic which
will help really
realize the illegals i think there's a
hunger for both of those
um and it's profound so yeah it doesn't
strike me as at all coincidental
that there's these simultaneously these
innovative new communities of ecclesia
coming into existence and then more
dynamically layered and dialectical and
symbolically informed
forms of christianity which are called
older which is completely right i think
are also coming into prominence um what
what needs to
well we need caution on both ends we
need
to avoid the conservatives bias
that the old is therefore better because
it's old
and the radical's biased that the new is
better precisely because
it's new uh and both of those
i think if left unreflected upon
and unchecked uh could make this go awry
in powerful ways like you could see
the the the the like you said you've
already said there's probably problems
with people trying to go back
like do you need to bring things back in
latin right right right
uh should we dress in roman tunics right
now how far back and what
and what what what's going and then of
course there's the you know the
innovation for the sake of innovation
which has become an intoxicant for our
culture
is also a particular bias uh so that's
the two pools of dialectic
either going all the way back to your
position where you don't change or going
all the way back to the other position
to which you're aspiring
and that's without like doing any uh
relationalization between the two to a
point that's actually fruitful to both
yeah and i think i would i think
i don't have a lot of time to talk about
it today but what's what what's coming
out as also a potential topic
is the relationship between relevance
realization and this function of
mediation
that you've been talking a lot about uh
because you know
uh obviously dialectic enhances
relevance realization and powerful ways
but as we've noted both within the
christian context and in the socratic
neoplatonic
context um it also enhances mediation
um in in important ways and that's
something
i'm also trying to reflect on um even
even the self-naming as philia sophia
someone who's always in love with wisdom
and never will come into
right a full possession of it um that
that's a that's a statement of that
we're inherently
the relevance realization is always a
mediating one um
what i would like at some point to
explore explore that
that that german idea with you a little
bit more too
yeah sure something going on there
because um
jonathan has made this argument to me
and then mary mary cohen
somebody you and i both talked with um
also powerfully made that argument
about you know and i noted it at the
time being important so it stuck with me
as a seed thought
you know that this role of mediation and
then you
independently uh but i think
convergently with mary's point
you know that that people when people
cease to experience
themselves as intermediaries
right um when that and so the
the model it's not only that the
monolithic mind was monological
and self-enclosed but it was also this
follows from it it was also
in no way a mediating mind and that's
also deep
your point is that's also been deeply
problematic and that's mary's point too
i think
this is something that needs to be it's
juicy i can feel it intuitively that
it's a juicy point
and it's it's filled with epistemic and
transformative juices
that we need to try and uh get back to
at some point maybe the three of us
should talk again at some point about
that topic yeah
yeah that'd be fun i'm sure she'd be
happy too do you know that uh jonathan
and paul and i are going to have a joint
uh dialogue soon yeah that would be
great because i think
that yeah the event in september
probably won't work in
international it's been yeah it's been
canceled that that event
well at least not it's been canceled but
like in the sense of postponed to when
it will be possible again
yeah yeah but uh yeah i was i was hoping
maybe i could go but i'll be very happy
to just listen to the three of you as
well
well yeah yeah
well that means we that brings a bit of
sadness to me because if we had had the
conference i would have got to meet you
in person as well
there's so many people that i've never
met in person and very much like to
is there i mean we're getting close to
an hour is there anything more
i mean we i think we touched a lot in a
very rich fashion
is there anything more you you want to
address or bring out on this
naturally quickly i do think
what you just said about real
naturalization coming into the mix is
relevant to another thing that i'd like
to talk about
it doesn't have to be today because it's
a big topic but i i think there's
something
there that could really help christians
such as me understand
miracles in a way that's not
too fraught with problems when when we
talked
just about a year ago about the
advantages and disadvantages of our
respective physicians
and one of the worries coming from a
religious side is you have to find a way
to
let's call if you if you
if you can bring miracles in your
ontology you have to do it in a way that
won't lead to you bullshitting
yourselves
yes and i do it does look to me like
whenever you look at something emerging
like there's always some aspect of a
miracle there and
some people you you see people often
within the religious side or even like
the pensacon side and so on
telling non-reductive physicalists that
well your idea of emergence is just
miraculous it doesn't work
but i i i'd like to use it the other way
around you know rather than saying that
it means that international physicalism
is like to be thrown the window i think
if we can use the uh the ideas and the
empirical research
around the emergence to better
understand how
somehow the the an overarching pattern
an overarching form
can meet with with potential with matter
in a way that explains this miraculous
emergence i think it could help
christians you know
better deal with the problematic
problematic aspects of miracles
it it looks like there's a continuity
there like if you look at anytime like
just a particle appears from the bottom
layer of physics it looks like a small
miracle
yes you look at the way when i make a
decision if you were to look at what
happens in my brain like all of the
coordination of all
different networks it would also look
like a miracle and
i think like at the highest scale if you
looked at let's see the incarnation and
all the different miracles that jesus
performed it you know it does look like
a miracle when you look at it at our
human level but if you take
let's see the theologian uh point of
view if you try to
see what's the meaning of those then it
can become part of a pattern
that that makes sense
all of a sudden and that also it's it
gives you a criteria for determining
which
miracles are real and which aren't that
doesn't just let's argue about the
material aspect of it but that's more
that is more concerned about the
overarching pattern in all of it
like does does the does the pattern make
sense in the same way that
if i were to to look at let's see my
decision uh
occurring when such and such miraculous
occurrences happen within my brain
that i could sort of map magnitude uh
so but it has to do directly with let's
see the role of relationalization
between dialectic how is it that
different you know that the many
in the potential can combine into
something
under a certain pattern so i i would
definitely hope that
to to have such a discussion at some
point don't i don't i would have more
time today but i don't know if you do as
well
yeah i don't have too much more time
today but we i i'm also very happy to
meet with you again and talk about this
i'd like to set this aside because uh
i i mean i set it aside for our next
meeting uh but
not dismiss it what i mean is uh
let's make a commitment i'm making a
commitment to let's have another
discussion about this
i like what you said there because um
sorry again between friends i've never
quite understood the commitment to
miracles i never
understood why it was like why is this
so important when does it matter
right like other and what i mean in a
non-question-making fashion i understand
if you're already committed
to a particular thing and it has
miracles within it
you there but you have a you have a
derived commitment to the miracles
within it
but there seems to be an independent
thing which is no you know i
i have an independent commitment to this
which i never understood but you you
just told it how about something that
was really really provocative are you
really cooking with gas today
the idea the idea that
there is emergence
carries within it some sense of the
creation
and i'll just point out that you know
for aerogena creation is precisely that
which
dialectically brings together emanation
and emergence
that's that's that's what creation is it
isn't just making
we we we've forgotten that making is a
model for creation it is not the same
thing as creation
so and what i heard you saying is
and i heard of i like whitehead was in
my head but you know whitehead said
everything comes to
all things come into one thing that is a
new thing that
right that there's inherent creativity
as whitehead puts it
right there and i think this is like
persist notion of quality too
what i heard you saying in all of these
notions
there is the creation of novelty
and the proper way of thinking about
that
is to see it as therefore miraculous
where miraculous doesn't mean
inconsistent or non-intelligible because
you mentioned deep continuity
but it's only until it's always only
intelligible after the fact
that's sort of a white-headed idea you
can't see it you can't from this side
predict the novelty because then it
wouldn't be novelty
but if it was just if if you couldn't
reconnect it backwards
it would just be absolute chaos yeah
right
yeah yeah it's meant it's meant to bring
us into something higher
um in the same way that when when i do
reverse rise
one revolutionization occurs and you can
see all of different networks coalescing
in a certain
pattern in my brain it's meant to bring
all of those different neurons
into an overarching pattern right like a
spark of the miraculous
miraculous novelty that brings the whole
constituents
forward and yes within a in a
father michael dodds whom i referenced
earlier in his
his book i really like this book it's
titled um
unlocking divine action and it uses
modern
notions uh within non-relative
physicalism to try and then make sense
of how
god can act for history and towards the
end of the book when he finally
you know has laid out of all the
machinery and he's able to leverage it
to talk about miracles and providence
and so on
he's able to say that well the goal of
miracles is precisely this is
that through different actions that god
can perform in the world
it will bring us into his own life it's
all to bring it's not meant to bring
creation into kind of itself or you can
see within
like whatever the ground is of relevant
translation the ground of emergency
nomination
like miracles matter because they
they they're like pointers for us to get
brought into
uh the divine life to get brought into
the very processes of
real menstrualization but if i
understood you
you're emphasizing that there
even in everyday events and this is
where i heard whitehead
the the notion of creative events even
in everyday events
uh you know of oxygen and hydrogen
coming together
this is the hackneyed example and water
emerging and water is novel in some way
to hydrogen and oxygen you're seeing
that that that
spark of novelty that so there's
there there's a you can say a deep
continuity right
yeah that's what i was going to say
there's a deep continuity between the
miraculous
and the natural in in what you're
proposing
yeah typically what uh what the language
that is often used and
this is modeled because i think
different people use different
definitions but
like typically people will talk about
providence
uh for everything that is like below
below i don't want to say the
supernatural it's not true like when
whenever
god acts directly whenever you can say
the whatever heaven and earth meet
directly
what you see will be miracles uh so at
the highest scale
when we would say in the incarnation
what what occurred there was
miracles but what occurs at lower levels
say the fact that uh
in our discussion today we're able to to
meet and we're able
to uh say meaningful things that neither
of us have thought about
quite well within within in christianity
this would be providence it's it's like
we have uh
an emergence of meaningful patterns that
you couldn't have predicted otherwise
that you can see that
the ground of relevance organization
still participated in that although at
the
more more common scale you can say than
what occurred at the incarnation
and it's even more common if you look at
this uh this is subatomic level
it's still a meeting of emergency
ammunition there that's really cool
because i i'm i i typically and i i
don't mean to be insulting i typically
don't find the notion of miracles
you know useful or helpful
my intelligence but what you did there
proposing sort of
it sounded to me like you proposed that
a deep continuity between miracles
providence
and something like the ground of being
or the you know
that's it you can sing maybe nature or
okay then okay yeah
yeah that's cool that's very interesting
wow
i would like to talk about this uh
because
because i would want to i mean
if you have pointers for what i could
think about for the next discussion you
know i'd be really happy to hear them
and ponder them
yeah well let me i mean the person that
keeps
coming to my mind right now is um is
whitehead there's i think it was
a book written by by rose on an
introduction to whitehead
it's a really it's a thin volume but
it's an excellent
um really good uh introduction to
whitehead
um and whitehead is of course deeply
influenced by brooks hall
but he's also doing um
what you've been doing and what we've
been talking about i mean
he proposes the notion of creative
advance
um as a way of
trying to understand the metaphysics
we're going to need in order to really
deeply understand science um he's deeply
informed
uh by the advances both at the
relativistic level and the quantum level
there's also um whitehead's book might
be really good religion in the making
and also um i'm going to be talking with
him
um oh i can't remember i think is it
matt
i think it's yeah it's matt segal um
he's got some videos
on um there's the future the future
faces of spirit
i have a video there and he talked and
he talks about uh sort of
the white-headed notion in language it's
very consonant with
uh the work i do but also very confident
with what we've been talking about
especially just now
so i think there's a there's there's
some yeah there's there's a lot of
people that are trying to
bring back this um
this i don't know i'm thinking of weber
here you know the just enchantment of
the world
they're trying to bring back an
enchanted view that is nevertheless uh
very rationally
and intellectually um responsible
so i think that's happening a lot right
now cool yeah i'll definitely check
those out
okay well that that's great so uh let's
make a commitment then
uh to talk maybe we could have a
discussion of on mediation and miracles
and uh and uh um and and try
and unpack that a little bit more yeah
yeah i look forward to it
so thank you so much jp and uh i hope
that you uh
you stay well and everything keeps uh
going smoothly for you thanks you too
john thanks